<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>What the Independents would have, or, A character, declaring some of their tenents, and their desires to disabuse those who speak ill of that they know not. / Written by John Cook of Grays Inne Barrister.</title>
            <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80413</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6031</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E405_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201877</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862366</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862366</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114523</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80413)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114523)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E405[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>What the Independents would have, or, A character, declaring some of their tenents, and their desires to disabuse those who speak ill of that they know not. / Written by John Cook of Grays Inne Barrister.</title>
                  <author>Cook, John, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114523:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>WHAT THE <hi>INDEPENDENTS</hi> Would have, <hi>OR, A</hi> CHARACTER, Declaring ſome of their Tenents, and their deſires to diſabuſe thoſe who ſpeak ill of that they know not.</p>
            <p>Written By JOHN COOK of <hi>Grays</hi> Inne Barriſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON, Printed for</hi> Giles Calvert, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114523:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114523:2"/>
            <head>What the INDEPENDENTS would have: or a Character declaring ſome of their TENENTS, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to diſabuſe thoſe who ſpeak ill of what they know not.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing called to the ſtudy of the great Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie of this age, many yeers ſince, by an occaſionall reſidence with ſome, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Independency of Churches, I ſtood as ſtiflly as I could, for Epiſcopacy: I read with a ſingle eye Maſter <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> Maſter <hi>Jacob,</hi> Maſter <hi>Robinſon,</hi> Maſter <hi>Johnſon,</hi> and every Book elſe I could finde of that ſubject <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Con,</hi> as concerning the Kingly office of Chriſt Jeſus to be the onely point worth ſtudying; and when the points of their arguments ſtuck ſo cloſe that I could not anſwer them, I grew angry (the Lord lay it not to my charge) and held a fair correſpondency with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in all the Ordinances, ſo long as I could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly get leave of my conſcience ſo to doe; and the queſtion truly ſtated, is but this; whether the inventions of men ought any more to be mixed with the Inſtitutions of Chriſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114523:3"/>in his Kingly Office, then their good works in his Prieſtly Office; which I am confident ere long, will be as much out of queſtion, as whether the Proteſtant or the Popiſh be the true Religion, whereof I hold it altogether impertinent to diſcourſe, it having been ſo cleerly vindicated by learned pens. But becauſe there is a great noiſe made, what would the Independents have? They never yet told us their deſires; the poore children are kept faſting all day, and then ſome rigid ſpirits like the curſt ſtep-mother (to whom they dare not ſpeak for feare of a flap on the mouth) quarrel with them; why, what would theſe untoward children have? Is any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy troubled with ſuch paltry Raſcals and harlotry baggages as I am? Theſe ſcurvy children make me weary of my life, when as ſhe knows, wel enough, it is bread that the children cry for. I ſhall tell you in a word what will content all the Independents in <hi>England;</hi> 'tis this; they deſire neither more nor leſſe, then what the Puritans deſired of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King <hi>James; viz.</hi> an entire exemption from the juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of all Prelates and Eccleſiaſticall Officers, other then ſuch as themſelves ſhall chooſe, and to be accountable to the Magiſtrate for what they ſhall do amiſſe, ſubmitting to the Civil Government in all things; &amp; to be lyable to all ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xations that by law are chargable upon perſons of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, not holding any opinions deſtructive of State-polity, not having a naturall tendencie to diſturbe the peace of the Kingdom, as all ſeditious practices have: but otherwiſe to be as free to chooſe their own company, place and time, with whom, where and when to worſhip God, as they are in the choice of their wives; for a forced marriage will not hold. This I ſay will ſatisfie all that goe under the name of Independents, which name and the word Presbyters, as it is uſed, I wiſh they were extinct and buried: If there muſt be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114523:3"/>a diſtinction, I wiſh rather they might be called <hi>Conformiſts</hi> and <hi>Reformiſts;</hi> but to give you an account of ſome of the Tenents of him that is properly and ſingularly called an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent by way of a Character.</p>
            <p>Hee is one that judges every man in a happy condition (though he hold many errours) that believes in Jeſus Chriſt, and is content to be every mans ſervant, ſo as Chriſt may but reign over his conſcience: which if hee ſhould not, hee knows not where hee is to reign; hee holds a ſubordination of Officers in the ſame Church, but an equality in ſeverall Congregations; which as ſiſters depend not upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but are helpfull as one hand to another; as God hath ordained a paritie and eminencie in power between ſeverall Kings and Princes, and that one ought not to invade the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Sovereigntie, not excepting againſt the conſultative, perſwaſive, and deliberative Synod, but the ruling Synod that ſhall command any thing, <hi>Imperio voluntatis,</hi> by a <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall</hi> authoritie without demonſtrating any utilitie or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to accrew thereby; and therefore an Independent is he, that depends not of any but Chriſt Jeſus, the Head in point of <hi>Canon</hi> and Command for Spirituall Matters; but is dependent upon man in all Temporall Matters abſolutely, and for Spirituals by way of adviſe and counſell, it being an Article of his Faith, that every man muſt be ſaved by his own faith, and knows no <hi>Medium</hi> between a reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and an Implicit faith; He counts the Royall Law of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie amongſt honeſt men to be the ſupreme law of the moſt noble Deſcent, to which all inferiour orders of Uniformitie muſt do homage, as the Ceremoniall Law to the Morall, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving every man that hath any thing of Chriſt in him, or common honeſty, and would not have Diſcipline breed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affection. Concerning the Diſcipline of Chriſts Church,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114523:4"/>does no more depend upon man then the doctrine; &amp; counts it the moſt glorious Light in the World to ſee Jeſus Chriſt walk as King, ruling by the Scepter of his Word in the midſt of his golden Candleſticks. Hee is ever privy to his owne infirmities, being far from dreaming of perfection in this life, therefore doth not ſeparate from mixt communions, becauſe he thinks himſelf too good, or better then his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, for he thinks himſelf the greateſt ſinner, being moſt privy to the deceitfulneſſe of his own heart,, and is ſure he hath more errours then he can diſcern, nor is it becauſe he would diſpleaſe any man, but becauſe he dares not diſpleaſe God, for he is fully perſwaded it is a ſin in him to doe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. He thinks no man will be godly, unleſſe he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be ſo; therefore wonders that any Chriſtian ſhould ſpeake againſt a Church Covenant, which is no more then to promiſe to doe that, by Gods aſſiſtance, which the Goſpel requires of him, yet will not ſay that it proceeds out of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of carnall liberty, or contempt of the ordinances; for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid cenſures ſeldome lodge in meeke and humble breſts; he eſteems proteſtation againſt practice, prevarication; as if <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hah</hi> had ſaid, though I lye with <hi>Reuben,</hi> my heart is honeſt to my husband; for one acre of performance, is worth a whole land of promiſe. He is a profeſſed enemy to all imperative, co-active violence in matters of conſcience, which are not an offence againſt civill juſtice, and thinks that to force men to come to Church is but to make them hypocrites. He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be content with an inferiour accommodation for his ſoul, when he may have a ſuperiour, going to the Ordinances to meet Jeſus Chriſt there, and to heare good news from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: he deſires to finde him in the fulleſt manner, but is not of ſo ſtrong a conſtitution as to faſt till authority ſettle a forme of worſhip. He holds the Word and Sacraments not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114523:4"/>to be the conſtitution of a Church (no more then the Law is the Common-wealth, or the axe the houſe) but the means and inſtrument of conſtitution, and counts him the onely extravagant man that flies from reaſon, which makes all men ſo noble: he is of an opinion that the far greater part of men in the Kingdom beleeve, that an honeſt, upright mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will win heaven, and hope ſo to live, as by their good works, Prayers, and good meanings to be ſaved, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore does not conceive theſe men to be viſible members of Chriſts body, and conſequently not to communicate in the diſtinguiſhing Ordinances; Hee thinks it ill done to enforce any under penalties to receive the Sacrament, poſſibly to ſeal up his own condemnation; he is for every reformed Church, ſo far as it is reformed; but ſays many Scotch Miniſters complain, that things are not thorowly reformed with them; hee counts it licentiouſneſs, not Chriſtian liberty, to affront thoſe that be in Authority, and never ſpeaks any thing againſt the Nationall way of worſhip, but to juſtifie his owne, if called thereunto. Hee will not be beaten but by Scripture weapons; and in reading Scriptures, neither ſtretches things wider, nor draws them narrower then God has made them; hee holds perſwaſion to be the Goſpellary way, and that liberty of Religion to all Proteſtants, is the bond of Religion againſt Papiſts; hee believes the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the faithfull in appearance to be the immediate receptacle of all eccleſiaſticall authority, and holds Non-communion with Churches, when one Church af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter faſting and Prayer, ſhall tell an hereticall company that it appears, they are in the ſtate of damnation, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and Publicans, and better a milſtone were hung about their necks then to give ſuch juſt offence, to be as effectuall to attain the ſpirituall end, as Excommunication: He is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114523:5"/>that Brethren ſhould fall out by the way, being all anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by one Spirit, as the body by one ſoul; but is glad that himſelf is not the leaſt cauſe of the diſagreement. He thinks ſpirituall diſeaſes muſt have ſpirituall cures, and thinks it is no proper way to confute an Heretick, to break his head with the Bible. Hee is one that deſires to live lovingly with all the World, and loves moſt where he ſees moſt of God; hee does not ſo much deſire that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould love him, becauſe he knows hee loves him already, nor that hee ſhould love him more, becauſe hee knows hee loves him enough, but that hee might love Chriſt and love him more; and hee joyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s himſelf in Church-fellowſhip, not to gaine Heaven, but to witneſſe his love to Jeſus Chriſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to love himſelf no farther then he finds the Image of God renewed in him.</p>
            <p>He counts it a great honour and ſecurity to Proteſtants to joyn all as one man againſt Popery, and deſires heartily a Union with our Brethren the <hi>Scots,</hi> which hee conceives may very well be without a Uniformity, which is a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the Saints above fully enlightned; hee thinks Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is <hi>ab eligendo,</hi> as well as <hi>à religando,</hi> and that the <hi>French</hi> Proteſtants are cordiall and ſincere, that may eyther goe to Maſſe or to Church, as they pleaſe. He conceives a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Presbytery, ſuch as men cannot except againſt, in point of Reaſon or Conſcience, is beſt conſiſtent with the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Kingdom, and why ſhould not moderate men be content with a moderate Diſcipline? He loves an honeſt Presbyterian better then an diſhoneſt Independent, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that the want of Morality excludes from Heaven; he believes that this Army would fight as heartily for the State againſt Popery, or any that ſhould doe them wrong, as ever they did for the Liberties of this Kingdom; and deſires that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:114523:5"/>the Parliament and Army would grant as much to the City of <hi>London,</hi> as may poſſibly conſiſt with the ſafety of the Kingdom. Hee freely forgives all thoſe that rail againſt him in Pulpits, and prays that God would make ſuch Miniſters more zealous to advance the power of godlineſſe then their own power.</p>
            <p>Hee deſires to learn the truth with all diligence and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and if for the preſent hee be in an errour, hee hopes all good Chriſtians will excuſe it, becauſe it proceeds from a deſire of all poſſible purity in a Congregation; as if a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant be over diligent, thinking to pleaſe his maſter, by doing his buſineſſe too well, no ingenuous man would blame him. He judges him the beſt Common-wealths man that wil ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer much himſelf, when it may conduce to the publike peace, and that is moſt forward to go in a way ſafe for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, though dangerous to himſelf: and him the beſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian that ſtudies Truth and Peace, yet ſo, as a Union of hearts rather then a vicinity of Houſes, is to make up a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation according to the New Teſtament, then which he conceives his way no Newer.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Errours of the times, many whereof pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend from weak judgements, but ſtrong affection to Jeſus Chriſt, he thinks all this ſmoak is not without ſome fire, but becauſe the common enemy, the Papiſts, have more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences among themſelves, leſt our jarring ſhould be their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, he deſires we may ſpend our wits upon them, and our charity upon one another; and if all truths be ſeaſonable, he conceives that the Aſſembly ſitting ſo long before they agreed upon any thing, was a great occaſioner of them; they kept the Kingdome too long faſting, as if all men had beene of a like ſtrong conſtitution, whereas paſſengers to heaven are in haſte, and muſt walk ſome way or other; and hee that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114523:6"/>hath gone far in a Wood is loth to turn back though hee be wrong; ſo dangerous is it to procraſtinate in their matters, and very rare for a man to confute himſelf. His practice is to baptize the children of one or both believing parents, as foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derally holy; the contrary opinion of ſome Anabaptiſts, or Antibaptiſts make him ſtudy Scripture in pietie, and devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion more; there being neither expreſſe precept nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for it, and the correſpondency of the Seals under both diſpenſations more, and poſſibly that may be a truth, which for want of light, hee conceives to be an errour; if it be an errour 'tis a very harmleſſe one, reſting there, and cannot diſturbe the publike Peace. If an <hi>Antinomian</hi> doctrinall doe not prove an <hi>Antinomian</hi> practicall, hee thinks ſome of thoſe opinions are very comfortable, and learns hereby, not to exalt duty too much, but to ſtudy free grace the more, and believe that the Doctrine of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſatisfaction, have never been more cleerly taught then by them that have been ſo called. He hopes Seekers finde the way to Heaven, yet counts it ſad that any ſhould wait for new Apoſtles (they may as well ſeeke a new Gopel,) and that thoſe Ordinances which Chriſt hath purchaſed with his pretious bloud ſhould be counted ſhadows, much derogatory to his love and wiſdome; yet he ſuſpects his own heart, and thinks that poſſibly ſome men live at a very high rate in ſpirituall enjoyments, being wholy at reſt in God, and have the leſſe need of Ordinances, and for thoſe that thinke the Saints are here in full perfection of grace and glory, his ſinfull heart tels him it is an errour; yet he will not judg any tree to be evil but by its fruits. He knows no hurt in a million of millenary-like errours; who would not be glad to ſee Jeſus Chriſt? That Chriſt died for all, he judges to be a great error, for then all muſt be ſaved, or poſſibly none may be ſaved, yet there are prudentiall reaſons and motives for it,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114523:6"/>as the Papiſts have for good works; if not meritorious, why commanded? If he dyed not for all, why is he preached to all? Yet the maintainers ayme is thereby to honour and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt Chriſt which is the great deſigne of the Father, and thereby his greater ſtudy &amp; ſo by different opinions he learns to doe things upon clearer principles, and ſo to walke in love and peace, as ſeeing him who is inviſible, and knows no reaſon, why their brethren (by the good leave of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the family, and Parliament) may not live lovingly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>He thinks it very abſurd that Popiſh Biſhops ſhould ordain Miniſters, as if the ſheep ſhould have no ſhepherds, but ſuch as the Wolves appoint; the rather for that the Apoſtles did not abridge the people of that liberty of chooſing an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, much leſſe may a Synod deprive them of chooſing their own Officers.</p>
            <p>He deſires no Toleration for any Errours againſt Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or State-policie, but of ſome errours in Religion which do not raze the foundation, conceiving liberty to be the beſt means to cure all ſuch differences, and that the Sword hath no capacity to ſettle Religion being not ſanctified to that purpoſe; and if impriſonment cure an heretick, 'tis but like his curing an enemy by letting out the Impoſtume, when he thought to kill him; for myſticall Wolves are to be kill'd myſtically; and therefore marvels that any politick Chriſtian ſhould oppoſe his deſires, for why may not he which five years ſince was for Biſhops, conſidering the wheeling viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and revolution of things, five years hence be an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent. Hee thinks compulſion is the onely way to make Hypocrites, and if Church Papiſts were ever accounted moſt dangerous, he wonders why men ſhould be forced to go to Church.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114523:7"/>
            <p>He thinks it ſtrange that Chriſtians ſhould have moſt wars who can leaſt juſtifie them, but conceives it is for want of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of conſcience. The Turke hath more colour to come with three or foure hundred thouſand men to invade this Kingdom, becauſe we are not of his Religion, then one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant hath to perſecute another. And he verily beleeves that if every man might take his Religion upon choyce and tryall, thouſands would be ſaved which dye ſecurely, making no queſtion of their ſalvation. He thinks it is a ſoloeciſme for Miniſters to bid men ſearch the Scriptures, when they may not profeſs that which they find to be true. He finds that this Kingdom hath had litle peace ſince the Biſhops baniſhed men into <hi>New England,</hi> where Independencie hath bin ſo far from being the root of evill, as it hath cured Schiſmes and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. He conceives the rigid Presbyters are notable Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to put the Parliament between themſelves and the envy of the people, for they do but untie the poynts, and deliver the party to the Magiſtrate to be whipt; as the Papiſts doe, who put Proteſtants to death, becauſe Proteſtants delight in perſecution, but wiſhes they would be moderate if they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to laſt, for the rigidneſs of the Biſhops was their ruine. He doth not finde any puniſhment in Scripture for tender conſciences, and by that politique Law which puts Idolaters to death, their cattell alſo were to be deſtroyed. He would gladly conforme to the preſent government, if he had his conſcience at command, in his own power, and knows no reaſon why carnall profeſſors ſhould oppoſe liberty, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deſire not to be troubled about Religion, but have it put into their mouthes by authority, which they hope will ſtand between them and harme. He conceives variety of opinions in circumſtantials, is, but as one ſtar differs from another; difference in hearts cannot hurt, nor difference in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114523:7"/>heads need not breed difference in hearts; and underſtands not why Covenants ſhould be made to repaire Caſtles in the aire, and ſince the moderate Diſciplinarians agree that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very congregation in <hi>America</hi> hath intireneſſe of juriſdiction, intrinſecally within it ſelfe, hee wonders that any man ſhould hold, that Churches are in worſe condition where the Magiſtrates profeſſe chriſtianity, or that it is not a favour that corporations may determine differences within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but he looks not at the likelyneſſe of the means, but Chriſts inſtitution, who is onely King of the conſcience, and conceives that all the world hath no more power over the conſcience then a Tinker hath, which can be no diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſay, that a ſtone hath as much life as the Sun. Hee conceives that <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. <hi>Tell the Church,</hi> are very plain words, but that learned men have inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted diſtinctions to make them intricate, and that Chriſt hath intruſted the keyes, to hang rather at his Spouſes girdle, then with the Stewards, and that a Churches cenſure being ratified in heaven, there can be no appeal on earth to any other Church.</p>
            <p>He conceives that ſuch a liberty will wonderfully indeare all conſcientious men to the Magiſtrate, the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; will gain the hearts of the people, without which all obedience will be uncordiall. Compulſion can no more gain the heart, then the fiſh can love the fiſher-man. As for thoſe arguments of diſorder and confuſion, the two Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall Scar-crows: he conceives they are but imaginary, vain fears, yet have been ſo drunk with the bloud of the Saints, that like <hi>Lycurgus Vines,</hi> he would never have them more urged; for an Heretike is but to be rejected, and as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, to be burnt with the fire of charity, nor ſhould we ſend them to hell who give no ſignes of repentance. He is an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable enemy to tyranny and popery, and it is the joy of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114523:8"/>heart, that God may have glory, though in his confuſion. He counts every godly Presbyterian to be his deare brother, but not to be preferred before the truth. He conceives that whoſoever is above his brother in ſpirituall matters (unleſſe impowred) is a pre ate; &amp; the onely way to make the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly more victorious then <hi>Alexander,</hi> is, by reaſon and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe to conquer conſciences without bloud. He conceives that Magiſtrate, in probability, to be more religious, that will ſuffer diffring opinions co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting with the publike peace, then he that <hi>Haman</hi>-like will have all to bow and ſtoop to his ſheaf; and that all the wars in <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> have ſprung from this one depraved principle, to ſuffer no opinion but his own, for how can truth appear but by argumentation? He thinks it a ſin either to follow an erring conſcience, or to doe againſt it, but to oppoſe it the greater ſin, for he that will doe the leaſt ſin againſt conſcience, is prepared in diſpoſition to doe the greateſt. He marvels any man ſhould hold Independen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie not to be Gods Ordinance, and yet a nationall Aſſembly to be Apoſtolicall, which is moſt Independent. He thinks there are many Deer without the pale, ſtraying ſheepe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a fold, and when all is done, there will be wolves within; &amp; lambs without; but think that to honour Chriſt is to do his wil, &amp; is moſt troubled to conſider how one ſheep ſhould bite and perſecute another. He beleeves the government of the Church, lies upon the ſhoulders of Jeſus Chriſt, and that the Pope may as well maintaine a Prieſthood under the Goſpel, after the example of <hi>Aaron,</hi> as that Magiſtrates may puniſh different opinions after the example of the godly Kings of <hi>Ifrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> who were types of Jeſus Chriſt, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected infallibly; and yet ſuffered <hi>Herodians, Alexandrians, Saduces</hi> and <hi>Phariſees;</hi> unleſſe the errours be of a morall and capitall conſideration, that may indanger the peoples welfare.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:114523:8"/>He verily beleeves that the ardent endeavours of the godly Presbyterians and Independents, are to conſerve the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in purity, and purging of the Church from ſcandall, and would fain beleeve that the difference between them is but ſmall, that the union may be the more eaſie, and ſees it moſt apparently, that the intereſt of all honeſt, godly men is wrapt up in a ſpeedy union, to love one another entirely, though of different judgements, otherwiſe Gods people are likely to be in a worſe condition for their liberties then ever they have been.</p>
            <p>He has ever been a faithfull wel-willer to King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, an enemy to all oppreſſion and cruelty, a reall friend to ſpeedy juſtice and urbanity, and thinks hee is no good neighbour that deſires it ſhould onely raine in his Garden; hee thinks all the delight in this World without the liberty of his conſcience, is a burthen intolerable. And judges Chriſts Kingdom to be onely there where his Laws are in force: for that County is no part of a Princes Dominion which is not regulated by his Laws. He is a homager to King and Parliament for the exerciſe of a good conſcience, not to beg liberty from man to be a Chriſtian, nor to ſettle the divine right of worſhip, but to be protected in the free exerciſe of it: hee cannot act contrary to his light received without manifeſt ruine of his owne ſoule, nor practiſe (but by the Magiſtrates permiſſion) without ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant hazard of his perſon and family, therefore intreats all Chriſtian ſpirits who have any credit with the Magiſtrate, and have felt the weight of an oppreſſed conſcience, to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate for him, as Men, Chriſtians, fellow-ſufferers, and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-helpers. Some think it the greateſt miracle in the world, that any generation of rigid men ſhould be ſo unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall to kill their own fathers, and perſecute their own bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114523:9"/>who but lately ſuffered with them: but concludes that ſuperſtition is an unreaſonable thing, and that Pride and Covetouſneſſe in ſome men, are enough to make a man of the <hi>Indians</hi> minde, by any means, not to be of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> Religion. Hee marvels any man ſhould be an enemy to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences, the want whereof is the plague of this wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked world, and that rich man that cannot feaſt till his poore neighbours have bread to eat, hath a tender conſcience. He knows no Injuſtice in an errour, or opinion, and marvels why believers ſhould contend about the faith, which they have already and can never loſe, and thinks it far better that Proteſtants, who in a Pariſh are of three opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſhould rather have three ſeverall meeting places, then fight and live in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall jars with one another; therefore reckons Liberty of Conſcience to be <hi>Englands</hi> chiefeſt good, becauſe nothing elſe can procure love and peace; for did God for the ſafety of a ſheep diſpence with his own law, and are men ſo Wolviſh to prefer an inferiour Law of uniformity to the royall law of love, which is the life of a Kingdome? but men may ruine themſelves, they can never ruine the truth. He thinks it a very uncivill part, for any man not to yeeld to a civill govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but in matter of opinion thinks it miſery enough to refuſe Chriſt Jeſus and ſalvation, and that to tye up the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man, unleſſe he be turbulent or unjuſt, is a reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for dogs and bears. He thinks it is but diſſembling for young people to contract themſelves, and after aske their friends conſents; to faſt and pray for that which is already reſolved upon, and believes that never did any bloudy <hi>Bonner</hi> perſecute any man under the notion of a Saint, but as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of evill, or diſturber of the State.</p>
            <p>He thinks it ſtrange that none but in office may preach, and yet one may preach to get an office, and how <hi>Beza,</hi> who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114523:9"/>was never ordained, could ordaine others, but he thinks there is leſſe need of an acceſſory ſolemnity then of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſalvation, and marvels why a man may not greach by his tongue as well as by his pen, the rather for that <hi>Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> ſent to his Princes to teach in the City of <hi>Judah.</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have preached in <hi>Geneva</hi> and Lairds in <hi>Scotland<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> not to be a Miniſter without an outward calling, but having an inward call, to preach to edification, though the line of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation were never ſtretcht over him; he thinks him not zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of mens ſalvation, that murmures at all mens preaching that are not faſhioned in his ſhop, and wiſhes that Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants would ſend men to preach Jeſus Chriſt to the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as well as Factors, for he thinks the true intereſt of <hi>England</hi> is the Proteſtant cauſe, to be as zealous to advance that, as the Spaniard is for popery. He thinks it impoſſible that the civill peace of a Kingdom ſhould be broken, unleſſe the Laws be violated; and how Lillies ſhould ſcratch, and Lambs tear Wolves, and Doves perſecute Hauks, and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ſcold, are things that lie very remote from his intellect.</p>
            <p>He thinks nothing more hinders a reformation then ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king things upon truſt, not ſupporting authority by ſolid reaſon. He wiſhes that every ingenuous man would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim all practices (ſpecially in matters of law) that are againſt the law of true reaſon; a confident adherence to authority, and a ready proſtration to Antiquity, preferring old Errours to new diſcoveries of Truth, being prime cauſes of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice and oppreſſion, as if an Argument from Authority were any proof to a wiſer man; a Generation of rigid Forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts making Religion overthrow it ſelf, by deſtroying mercy and Humanity. 'Tis well for many ſcandalous Railers, that he is a man of a peaceable ſpirit; and all the hurt that he wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes to the Kingdom, is, that Independents were the worſt men in it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114523:10"/>
            <p>He draws his ſword for publike Liberties, which being ſubſtantially ſetled by King and Parliament, and ſecured, He will gladly ſheath it, and ſay, <hi>The Lord hath done all;</hi> and hope; that no ingenuous man will envy him thoſe Liberties which were purchaſed for him by the bloud of Chriſt, knowing that a Communion in Unity will be a glorious ſupplement to the rent of Uniformity, which may ſeeme ſtrange for a time, but will quickly be embraced by all honeſt men. A ſolid Reaſon will at any time convince him, and hee loves to read diſcourſes which are rationall, therefore to charge him with wilfulneſſe and obſtinacy is a ſupercilious and cenſorious ſeverity, if not an uncivill and unchriſtian offence: for God is the ſearcher of all hearts. To whoſe grace and goodneſſe, he commends the courteous Reader.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
